Moby Dick or the Whale by Herman Melville.
Prologus.
Etmology supplied by a late consumptive usher to a grammar school.
The pale usher threadbearon coat, heart, body, and brain. I see him now. he was
ever dusting his old lexicons and grammarss with a queer handkerchief
mockingly embellished with all the gay flags of all the known nations of the
world. He loved to dust his old grammarss, it somehow mildly reminded him of his mortality.
Quote, "While you take in hand to school others, and to teach them by what name a
whalefish is to be called in our tongue, leaving out through ignorance the letter
H, which almost alone maketh the signification of the word, you deliver
that which is not true." Hacklit quote whale Swedish and Danish Val. This
animal is named from roundness or rolling for in Danish haval is arched or vaulted.
Webster's dictionary quote whale it is more immediately from
the Dutch and German volin anglosaxon vian to roll to wallow Richardson's dictionary kitos Greek
ketus Latin well Anglo-Saxon hav Danish Val, Dutch, Val, Swedish, Val, Icelandic,
Whale, English, Balain, French, Balena, Spanish, Pikinui Nui, Fiji, Piki Nui Nui, Aeromanguin